<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for the Kings Maiesties most gracious, generall, and free pardon</title>
            <title>Public General Acts</title>
            <author>Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836959</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1260</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1260)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1384:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for the Kings Maiesties most gracious, generall, and free pardon</title>
                  <title>Public General Acts</title>
                  <author>Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Society of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXXV [1635]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: a-b⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within woodcut architectural frame.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Anno X. &amp; XI. caroli regis.</note>
                  <note>Considerable print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1260:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1260:1"/>
            <p>AN ACT FOR THE KINGS MAIESTIES MOST GRACIOVS, GENERALL, AND FREE PARDON.</p>
            <p>DUBLIN, <hi>Printed by the Society of Stationers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M.DC.XXXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:1260:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1260:2"/>
            <head>Caroli Regis. AN ACT FOR THE KINGS MAIESTIES MOST GRACIOVS, GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAL, AND FREE PARDON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kings Maieſtie, moſt graciouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the good-will, and faithfull hearts of his moſt louing and obedient Subiects, which as at all times, ſo at this preſent eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, they hauing with moſt dutifull affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhewed towards his Highnes, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that the ſame his louing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, haue many and ſundry wayes, by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, falue into the danger of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers great penalties &amp; forfeitures, is of his Princely and merciful diſpoſition, moſt graciouſly inclined, to extend vnto them, his libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and free Pardon, truſting they wilbe the rather moued &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced henceforth, more carefully to obſerue his Highnes Lawes &amp; Statutes, and to continue in their legall &amp; due obedience to his Maieſtie. And therefore his Maieſtie is well pleaſed and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that it bee enacted by the authoritie of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and be it enacted by the authority of the ſame, in manner and forme following, (that is to ſay) That all and euery the ſaid Subiects, aſwell Spirituall, as Temporall, of this his Highnes Realme of Ireland, the Heires, Succeſſors, Executors, &amp; Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators of them, &amp; euery of them, &amp; all and ſingular bodies, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manner of wiſe corporated, Litties, Burroughs, Shires, Hundreds, Baronies, Townes, Villages, Hamlets, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, and euery of them, and the Succeſſor and Succeſſors of euery of them, ſhal be by the authority of this preſent Parliament, acquitted, pardoned, releaſed, &amp; diſcharged, againſt the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, his Heires, and Succeſſors, and euery of them, of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Treaſons, Felonies, Offences, Contempts, Treſpaſſes, Entries, Wrongs, Deceits, Miſdemeanors, Forfeitures, penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſummes of money paines of death, paines corporall and pecuniarie, and generally, of all other things, cauſes, quarrells, ſuits, iudgments, and executions, in this preſent Act, hereafter not excepted, nor fore-priſed, which may be, or can be, by his Highnes in any wiſe, or by any meanes pardoned; before, and vnto the three and twentieth day of May laſt paſt, to euery, or any of his ſaid Subiects, Bodies corporate, Cittyes, Burroughs, Shires, Hundreds, Baronies, Townes, Villages, and Tythings, or any of them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1260:3"/>
            <p>And alſo the Kings Maieſtie is contented, that it be enacted by authoritie of this preſent Parliament, and be it enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the ſame, that this his ſaid free Pardon, ſhal be as good &amp; effectuall in the Law, to euery of his ſaid Subiects, bodies Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, and others before rehearſed, in, for, and againſt all things, which be not hereafter in this preſent Act, excepted &amp; fore-priſed, as the ſame pardon ſhould haue been, if all offences, contempts, forfeitures, cauſes, matters, ſuits, quarrells, iudgements, executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, penalties, and all other things, not hereafter in this preſent Act, excepted and fore-priſed, had beene particularly, ſingularly, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, and playnely, named, rehearſed, and ſpecified, &amp; alſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by proper and expreſſe words, and names, in their kindes, natures, and qualities, by words and tearmes thereunto requiſite to haue beene, put in, and expreſſed, in this preſent Act of free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: And that his ſaid Subiects, nor any of them, nor the Heires, Executors or Adminiſtrators of any of them, nor the ſaid bodies corporate, and others, before named and rehearſed, nor any of them be, nor ſhal be ſued, vexed, or inquieted in their Bodies, Goods, Chattles, Lands, or Tenements, for any manner of matter, cauſe, contempt, miſdemeanor, forfeiture, treſpaſſe, offence, or any other thing, ſuffered, done, or committed, before the ſaid three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of May laſt paſt, againſt his Highneſſe, his Crown, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity, prerogatiue, Lawes, or Statutes, but onely for ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, cauſes, and offences, as be rehearſed, mentioned, or in ſome wiſe touched in the exceptions of this preſent Act, to be forepriſed and excepted, and for none other; any Statute or Statutes. Lawes, Cuſtomes, or Vſages, heeetofore had, made, or vſed to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And the Kings Highneſſe, of his bounteous liberality, by the authority of this preſent Parliament, granteth, and freely giueth to euery of his Subiects, and to euery of the ſaid bodies corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, &amp; other before rehearſed, and euery of them, all Goods, Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, debts, fines, iſſues, profits, amerciaments, forfeitures, and ſummes of money, by any of them forfeited, which to his Highnes doe, or ſhould belong, or appertaine, by reaſon of any offence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, treſpaſſe, entry, miſdemeanor, matter, cauſe, or quarrell, ſuffered, done, or committed, by them, or any of them, before the ſaid three &amp; twentieth day of May laſt paſt, which bee not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in this preſent Act, fore priſed and excepted.</p>
            <p>And be it enacted neuertheleſſe, that all grants thereof, or of any part thereof, made by any ſuch, as haue ſo forfeited the ſame, and are hereby reſtored, as aforeſaid, and all Executions thereof, or of any part thereof, had againſt any ſuch, after ſuch forfeiture thereof, committed or made, ſhall be of ſuch force, and effect, as if no ſuch forfeiture thereof had beene had, or made, and of no other, The ſame forfeiture, or any thing before in this Act to the contrary, notwithſtanding. And that all &amp; euery the Kings ſaid Subiects,
<pb facs="tcp:1260:3"/>and all and ſingular bodies corporate, &amp; others before rehearſed, may by him, or themſelues, or by his, or their Deputie, or Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or by his, or their Attourney, or Attourneyes, according to the Lawes of this Realme, plead, and miniſter this preſent Act of free pardon, for his, or their diſcharge, of, &amp; for any thing, that is by vertue of this preſent Act pardoned, diſcharged, giuen, or gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, without any Fee, or other thing paying, to any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for writing, or entry of the Iudgments, or other cauſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch plea, writing, or entry, but only ſixteene pence, to bee payed to the Officer, or Clerke, that ſhall enter ſuch plea, matter, or Iudgment, for the parties diſcharge in that behalfe: any Law, Statute, Vſage, or Cuſtome to the contrary, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, the Kings Maieſtie is contented &amp; pleaſed, That it be enacted by the authority of this preſent Parliament, that this his ſaid free pardon, by the generall words, clauſes, and ſentences before rehearſed, ſhal be reputed, deemed, adiudged, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, allowed, &amp; taken, in all manner of Courts, of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and elſewhere, moſt beneficiall, and availeable, to all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular the ſaid Subiects, bodies corporate, and others before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, &amp; to euery of them, in all things not in this preſent Act, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, or fore-priſed, without any ambiguitie, queſtion, or other delay, whatſoeuer it ſhall be, to be made, pleaded, obiected, or alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, by the King our Soueraigne Lord, his Heires, or Succeſſors, or by his, or any of their generall Attourney, or Atourneyes, or by any perſon or perſons, for his Highneſſe, or any of his Heires, or Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, it is enacted by the King our Soueraigne Lord, and by the authoritie of this preſent Parliament, That if any Officer, or Clerke, of any his Highneſſe Courts, commonly called the Chantery, Kings Bench, and Gommon-pleas, or of his Exchequer, or any other Officer, or Clerks, of any other of his Highneſſe Courts, within this Realme, at any time after the laſt day of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, make out, or write out any manner of Writs, proceſſe, ſummons, or other precepts, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any of the ſaid Subiects, or any of the ſaid bodies corporated, or others before rehearſed, or any of them, ſhal be in any wiſe arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, attached, diſtreyned, ſummoned, or otherwiſe vexed, inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or grieued, in his, or their bodies, Lands, Tenements, Goods or Chattles, or in any of them, for, or becauſe of any manner of thing pardoned, or diſcharged, by vertue of this Act of free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: or if any Sheriffe, or Eſcheator, or any of their Deputie, or Deputies, or any Bayliffe or other Officer whatſoeuer, by colour of his, or their Office, or otherwiſe after the ſaid laſt day of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, doe levie, receiue, take, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, of, or from any perſon or perſons, any thing pardoned, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by this Act, that then euery ſuch perſon ſo offending, and thereof lawfully convicted or condemned, by any ſufficient Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb facs="tcp:1260:4"/>witneſſe, or proofe, ſhall yeeld, and pay for recompence ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the partie ſo grieued or offended thereby, his, or their treble damages, beſides all coſts of the Suit, &amp; ſhall alſo forfeit &amp; looſe to the Kings Maieſty, for euery ſuch default, Ten pounds: And neuertheleſſe all and ſingular ſuch Writs, proceſſe, and precepts ſo to be made, for, or vpon any manner of thing pardoned, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by this preſent Act of free pardon, ſhall be vtterly voyde, and of none effect.</p>
            <p>Excepted and alwayes fore-priſed, out of this generall and free pardon, all, and all manner of high Treaſons, &amp; other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, committed, or done by any perſon or perſons, againſt the King or Queenes moſt Royall perſons, or either of them, or the perſon of the Prince his Highneſſe, and all conſpiracies and confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, trayterouſly had, committed, or done by any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, againſt the King, or Queenes Maieſties Royall perſons, or either of them, or the perſon of the Prince his Highnes; and all, and all manner of levying of Marre, and all Rebellions, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections whatſoeuer: And alſo excepted all &amp; euery manner of Treaſons, committed or done, by any perſon or perſons, in the parts beyond the Seas, or in any other place out of the Kings Dominions: And alſo all ſuits, puniſhments, executions, paines of death, forfeitures and penalties, for, or by reaſon, or occaſion of any the Treaſons and offences before excepted.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this pardon, all offences of forging, &amp; falſe counterfeiting the Kings Maieſties Great, or privy Seale, ſigne Manuell, or priuy Signet, or of any the Moneyes currant within this Realme: And alſo all offences of vnlawful diminiſhing of any the ſaid Moneyes, by any way or meanes whatſoeuer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Lawes &amp; Statutes of this Realme: And alſo excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of this generall pardon, all other Treaſons whatſoeuer, of what nature, kinde, or quality ſoeuer: And alſo all miſpriſions and concealements of high Treaſon; And all abetting, ayding, comforting, or procuring of the ſame offences, or any of the ſaid Treaſons.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this pardon, all manner of voluntary Murders, petit Treaſons, and willfull poyſoning, done, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, by any perſon or perſons, and all and euery the acceſſaries to the ſame offences, or any of them, before the ſaid offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted and fore-priſed out of this generall Pardon, all and euery offences of Piracy, and Robbery, done vpon the Seas, and all &amp; euery procuring or abbetting of any ſuch offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and the comforting &amp; receiuing of them, or any of them, or of any goods taken away by way of piracy, or robbery, vpon the Seas, as aforeſaid, or of any goods, forfeited, or due vnto his Maieſtie, by reaſon of any piracy, or robbery vpon the Seas.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this pardon, all Burglaryes, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:1260:4"/>or done, in any dwelling-houſe, or houſes, and all acceſſaryes to any the ſaid Burglaryes, before the ſame Burglary commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all Robberyes, done vpon, or to any mans or womans perſon in the high-way, or elſe where: And all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular acceſſaryes, of, or to any ſuch Robberies, before the ſaid Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery committed: And alſo excepted the fellonious ſtealing of any Horſe, Gelding; Garran, or Mare, and all acceſſaryes thereunto, before the ſame felony committed, and all Iudgments and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of, and for the ſame: And alſo excepted all willfull burnings of any dwelling houſe, or houſes, or of any Barne or Barnes, wherein any Lorne was.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted the deteſtable and abhominable vice of Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, committed with Mankind, or Beaſts. And alſo excepted all Rapes, and carnall Rauiſhments of Women.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all rauiſhments, and willfull taking away or marrying of any Mayde, Widdow, or Damoſell, againſt her will, or without the aſſent or agreement of her parents, or of ſuch as then had her in cuſtody: And alſo all offences of ayding, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting, procuring, or abetting of any ſuch raviſhment, willfull ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or marrying, had, committed, or done.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all willfull Eſcapes of any Traytors.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this pardon, all perſons, now attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or out-lawed, of, or for any Treaſon, petit Treaſon; Murder, willfull poyſoning, Burglary, or Robbery, and all Executions, of and for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted, all offences of Invocations, Coniurations, Witch-crafts, Sorceries, Inchantments, &amp; Charmes; and all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of procuring, abetting, or comforting of the ſame, and all perſons now attained, or convicted of any of the ſaid offences.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all and euery perſon &amp; perſons, which being out-lawed of, or for any felony, or felonies, and their out-lawries; ſtanding in force ſithence the ſaid outlawries haue eftſoones com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted any other felony.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all and euery manner of taking from the Kings Maieſtie of any Goods or Chàttles, or the Iſſues, Rents, Reuenues, or Droſits, of any Manors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, which were of any Traytor, Murderer, Fellon; Clerke, or Clerkes, attainted, or convicted, or Fugitiues, or any of them.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted, all Goods and Chattles, in any wiſe forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Kings Maieſtie, by reaſon of any Treaſon, petit Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Murder, or Felonie heretofore committed, or done.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted, all offences, of, or in making, Writing, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or publiſhing, or in conſenting vnto the making, writing, printing, or publiſhing, of any falſe, ſeditions, or ſcandalous Book or Bookes, Libell or Libells, in any wiſe againſt the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,
<pb facs="tcp:1260:5"/>or the preſent gouernment of this Realme, in cauſes either Eccleſiaſticall, or Temporall, or againſt any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all intruſſons, had, made, or done, by any perſon or perſons, in, or vpon any the Manors, Lands, Tenements, or other Hereditaments of the Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and all waſtes, done, committed, or ſuffered, vpon any ſuch Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments; and the wrongfull taking of any the rents, iſſues, and profits of the ſame Manors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, of the Kings Highneſſe: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all Suits, Accompts &amp; Impetitions, of and for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon all Alienations, made of and Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, with out licence, and all fines, iſſues, &amp; proſits, that may, or ought to grow, or come to the Kings Maieſtie, by reaſon of any ſuch Alienation, without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all waſtes committed, or done, in any of the Kings Wards-Lands, or in the Wards-lands of any of the Kings Committees: And alſo all and euery Fine &amp; Fines, for the ſingle &amp; double value of the Marriage, or Marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, of all &amp; euery Ward or Wards, at any time heretofore grown to the Kings Maieſtie, ſithenee the beginning of his Maieſties Raigne.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted, all Wards, and the Lands of ſuch Wards, as haue growne to the Kings Maieſtie, ſithence the beginning of his Maieſties Raigne: and all Liveryes, Primer Seiſins, &amp; Ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-lemains, that ought to be had, done, or ſued, for, or in reſpect of any the Ward or Wards-Lands, before excepted.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this generall Pardon, all rauiſhments &amp; wrongfull taking, &amp; with-holding of any of the Kings Wards, or Wards-Lands before excepted, or the rents and profits of the ſame, &amp; all miſdemeanors &amp; offences concerning the ſame. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing that by reaſon of any Ward, or Wards-Lands before excepted, or for default of ſuing, or proſecuting of any Livery of the ſame, ought to come, or be to the Kings Maieſtie, &amp; which as yet is not diſcharged.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all Fines that ſhould, or ought to grow to the Kings Maieſtie that now is, of any of his Widdowes, that haue marryed without Licence, ſince the beginning of his Maieſties Raigne.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and bee it enacted by the authority of this preſent Parliament, That the Kings Maieſtie, his Heires and Succeſſors, ſhall haue and inioy, the full &amp; whole Intereſt, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, Profit, and advantage of all Wardſhips before excepted, and of all Liveryes, Primer Seiſins, and Duſter lemaines, of all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, whatſoeuer, and all means iſſues, rates, &amp; profits, for not proſecuting, or not ſueing
<pb facs="tcp:1260:5"/>of any Liuery, or Ouſter-lemaine, happening, growing, or accrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſithence the begining of his Maieſties Raigne; as if this Act had neuer been had or made.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, and be it enacted, That all and euery perſon &amp; perſons, which haue tendered, or ought to ſue, his, her, or their, or any of their Liueryes, or Ouſter-lemaines, of, or for any Manors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, whatſoeuer they bee, ſhal ſue his, her, or their Liuery, &amp; Liueryes, and Ouſter lemaines; out of our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the Kings hands, and ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere &amp; pay their fines, iſſues, &amp; meane profits, for his, or their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Lands, Tenements, &amp; Hereditaments, which haue growne and accrewed ſithence the beginning of his Maieſties Raigne, in like manner and forme, to euery reſpect, as they, &amp; euery of them, ſhould, or ought to haue done, if this Act had neuer beene had, nor made; notwithſtanding the not finding of any Office, or Offices, or any other matter whatſoeuer; any article, thing, or things, to this preſent Act of generall Pardon, compriſed, and ſpecified to the contrary, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted and fore-priſed out of this Pardon, all ſuch perſons, as the laſt day of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, bee in priſon within the Caſtle of Dublin, or in the priſon of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalſey of the foure Courts, or otherwiſe reſtrayned of liberty, by expreſſe commandement, or directions of the Lord Deputy, or of any his Mateſties Priuy Louncell.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all and euery ſuch perſon &amp; perſons, which at any time ſithence the beginning of the Raigne of our late moſt gracious Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> of bleſſed memory, haue fled out of this Realme of Ireland, or any other his Maieſties Dominions, for any offence of high Treaſon, petit Treaſon, or miſpriſon of Treaſon.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all ſuch perſons as be gone or fled out of this Realme, for any cauſe, contrary to the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, without the Licence of the Kings Maieſtie, or of the Lord Deputy, or other thieſe Gouernour, or Gouernours of this Realme.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all ſuch perſons, as haue obtayned &amp; had Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to depart this Realme for a certaine time, and now doe abide out of the Realme, without any lawfull excuſe, after the time of their Licence expired.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all and euery conceale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and wrongfull detaynments, of any Cuſtome, Subſidie, Poundage, or Impoſt, due to the Kings Maieſtie that now is, &amp; all corruptions and miſdemeanors of any Officer, or Miniſter of, or concerning any Cuſtome, Subſidie, Poundage, or Impoſt, and all accompts, impetitions, and ſuits to bee had, made, or done for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all and ſingular accompts, of all and euery
<pb facs="tcp:1260:6"/>Collector and Collectors of any Subſidie, Poundage, Cuſtome, Impoſition, Compoſition, or other thing; &amp; all accompts of euery other perſon whatſoeuer, that ought to bee accomptant to the Kings Highneſſe, and the Heires, Executors, and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, of euery ſuch perſon, that ought to accompt for all things touching onely the ſame accompts: And all and ſingular Arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of accoinpts, &amp; vutrue accompts, and all impetitions, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Seiſures, Suits, Demaunds, and Executions, which may, or can bee had, of, or for any ſuch accompt or accompts, or any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerages of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all titles and actions of <hi>Quare impedit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all homages. And alſo excepted all reliefe, and reliefes, heriots, rents-ſeruices, reuts-charges, rents-ſerkes, &amp; the arrerages of the ſame, not done or payde to the Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all conditions, and couenants, and penalties, titles and forfeitures of condition, or conditions, couenant, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenants, acctued, or geowne to the Kings Mareſtie, by reaſon of the breach, &amp; not performing of any couenant, or condition what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all ſummes of Money, granted to the Kings Maieſtie that now is, or any of his noble Progeuitors, by way or name of Subſidie, contribution, compoſition, or otherwiſe, and all concealements, fraudes and offentes, by which his Maieſtie hath beene deceiued, and not truly anſwered, of, or for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all debts, which were, or be due to onr Soueraigne Lord the King, or our late moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> of ſamous memory, (his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Royall Father,) or to any perſon or perſons, for, or to any of their vſes, by any condemnation, terognizance, obligation, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, (other theu ſuch debts as are due, vpon any obligation, or recognizauce, forfeited before the ſaid three &amp; twentieth day of May laſt paſt, for not keeping the peace; or not being of good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour) which debts geowne, or accrewed vpon theſe cauſes, <hi>viz.</hi> for not keeping of the peace, of not being of the good behauior, by this free Pardon, be, &amp; ſhall be, clearely pardoned and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted &amp; fore-priſed out of this Pardan, all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular penalties, forfeitures, and ſummes of money, being due, or accrewed to our Soueraigne Lord the King, by reaſon of any Act, Statute, or ſtatutes, which forfeitures, panalties, &amp; ſummes of money, be converted into the nature of debts, by any Iudgment, order, or decree, or by the agreement of the offend or, or offendors, fithence the beginning of the raigne of our late gracious. Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne King <hi>Iames</hi> of ſamous meinory.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all forfeitures of all Leaſes, Eſtates, or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, of any Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, holden of
<pb facs="tcp:1260:6"/>out Soueratgue Lord the Kings Maieſtie, by knights ſeruice, or in ſorage, in <hi>Capite,</hi> or otherwiſe by knights ſeruice, made in one, or ſeuerall aſſurances, or leaſes, for any tearme, or tearmes of yeares, whereupon the olde and accuſtomed rent, or more, is not reſerued.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all firſt fruits, and twentieth parts, growne due, ſince the beginning of his Maieſties Raigne, and at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent being due to be payed to his Maieſtie, by force of any Act, or Statute, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted, all penalties and forfeitures, whereof there is any verdier, ſince the beginning of his Maieſties Raigne, in any ſuite giuen, or paſt for the Kings Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all forfeitures, and other penalties and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, now due, accrued, and growne, or which ſhall, or may be due, accrow, or grow to the Kings Maieſtie, by reaſon of any offence, miſdemeanor, or contempt, or other Act, or Deed, had, ſuffered, committed, or done, contrary to any Act, Statute, or Statutes, or contrary to the common Lawes of this Realine, and whereof, or for the which, any action, bill, plaint, or information, at any time within eight yeares, next before the laſt day of this preſent ſeſſion of Parliament, hath beene, or ſhal be exhibited, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menced, or ſued in the Courts of Caſtie-Thamber, or Exchequer-Chamber, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Kings Maieſties Courts at Dublin, &amp; now is, or the ſaid laſt day of this Seſſion of Parliament, ſhall be there depending &amp; remaining, to be proſecuted, or whereof the Kings Maieſtie by his Letters Pattents, vnder his great Seale of England, or Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, or by any Letter, or Warrant, vnder his Highneſſe priuy ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of England, hath heretofore made, or directed to be made, any gift. or aſſignment to any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this generall &amp; free pardon, all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, contempts, diſorders, covins, frauds, deceits, &amp; miſdemeanors whatſſoeuer heretofore committed, or done, by any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; whereof, or for the which any ſuite, by bill, plaint, or infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, at any time within foure yeares, next before the laſt day of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, is, or ſhall be commenced, or exhibited in the Tourt of Caſtle-Chamber at Dublin, &amp; ſhall be there, the ſame laſt day of this Seſſion of Parliament depending, or whereupon any ſentence, or decree, is giuen or entred.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all offences of periuries, &amp; the ſubornation of witneſſes, &amp; offences of forging, &amp; counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting of any falſe deeds, eſcripts or writings, or of any examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or teſtimonies of any witneſſe, or witneſſes, tending to bring an perſon or perſons, into danger of his life, and the giuing of the ſame in evidence, &amp; the counſelling, or procuring of any ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting or forgeing, to be had, or made. And all falſe &amp; malicious conſpiracies, to bring any perſon or perſons, into danger of his life.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all &amp; euery offence or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences,
<pb facs="tcp:1260:7"/>touching, or concerning the carrying, ſending, or convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer the Seas, out of this Realme, of any gold, ſiluer, Iewels, or any coyne of gold, or ſiluer, coutrary to the lawes, or Statutes of this Realme, vnleſſe it were by the licence of the Kings Maieſtie, or of the Lord Deputie, or other chiefe Gouernour, or Gouernors of this Realme.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all offences of Hereſſe, Schiſme, Inceſt, Adultery, Fornication, &amp; Simonie, &amp; all Uſury, where any intereſt hath beene receiued, or taken, aboue the rate &amp; proportion of ten pounds, for the loane or forbearance of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds for one yeare; and ſo ratably, for a greater, or leſſer ſumme, or for a longer, or ſhorter time: &amp; all miſdemeanors, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances, committed, or made, in any Church, or Chappell, in the time of Common-prayer; preaching, or diuine ſeruice there v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to the diſturbance thereof, &amp; all out-lawries, &amp; proſecutions v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſame.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all offences of drawing of Weapons, vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtriking, or giuing of blowes, &amp; all other force &amp; violence, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or done, in any Tearme-time, in the view of any the Kings Courts iudicially ſitting, at, or in the kings Courts at Dublin, or defore the Iudges of Aſſize, in their ſeuerall Circuits, for the which, any perſon or perſons, now ſtand indicted, convicted, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted, in any of his Maieſties ſaid Courts.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all offences, wherby any perſon may be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the penaltie &amp; danger of <hi>Praemunire,</hi> &amp; of the which offence or offences, any perſon ſtandeth already indicted, or otherwiſe lawfully condemned, or convicted.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all dilapidations, for which any Suite is, or before the end of this Seſſion of Parliament, ſhal be depending.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all offences whatſoeuer in Shipping, or willingly aſſenting, or cauſing to bee ſhipped to bee tranſported into any the parts beyond the Seas, out of the obedience of his Mateſtie, any Gunnes, Ordinance, Shot, or Gun-mettall, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Lawes &amp; Statutes of this Realme, without Licence of his Mateſtie, or of the Lord Deputie, or other chiefe Gouernour or Gouernors of this Realme, in that behalfe firſt had &amp; obtained. And alſo all ſuch as covenouſly, or by conſent, or for the reliefe of any ſuch as haue offended, in, or againſt any popular, or penall Statute, haue for the ſame offence, or offences, exhibited any acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bill, plaint, information, or ſuit, againſt any ſuch offendor or offendors.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all offences, in taking away, imbezelling, or purloyning, any the kings Maieſties Goods, Money, Chattles, Iewels, Armor, Munition, Ordinance, or Habiliments of warre.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this pardon, all manner of Extortions &amp; Briberies whatſoeuer: And alſo excepted all covins, fraudes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, &amp; other diforders, &amp; miſdemeanors whatſoeuer, heretofore
<pb facs="tcp:1260:7"/>committed, or done, by any Steward of his Maieſties Manors or Courts, Sheriffe, or Under ſheriffe, or by any officer, or miniſter, in any of his Highnes Courts, or any wayes truſted, or imployed, in, or about his Maieſties Lands, or Reuenue, in, or by reaſon or colour of any of their offices, or places, or any their Deputies, or Clerkes; &amp; all offences of ayding, comforting, aſſiſting, or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of any Sheriffe, Under-ſheriff, or any ſuch Officer, Miniſter, or Clerke, in contriuing, doing, or executing any ſuch extortion, exaction, covin, fraud deceit, diſorder, or miſdemcanor.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all Iſſues, Fines, &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciaments, loſt, impoſed, aſſeſſed, offered, or taxed, ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Maieſties Raigne.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all Iſſues, Fines, &amp; Amerciaments, returned, afferred, taxed, ſet, or entred, ſeuerally, or particularly, in any Court of Record at Dublin. And yet neuertheleſſe, his Maieſtie of his abundant grace &amp; fauour, towards all his louing Subiects, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into his gracious &amp; Princely conſideration that many of his ſaid Subiects, haue beene &amp; yet are, continually to their exceeding great charges &amp; expences, troubled &amp; moleſted for ſundry &amp; diuers Iſſues, Fines, Amerciaments, forfeited Recognizances, &amp; other forfeitures due to his Maieſtie, which bee continually written for <hi>in ſchedula Pipe,</hi> in his Maieſttes Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, is graciouſly pleaſed, that it bee enacted, &amp; bee it enacted by the authoritie aforeſaid; That all ſuch Iſſues, Fines, Americi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments, forfeited Recognizances, &amp; other forfeitures, as before the ſaid 23. day of May laſt paſt haue been drawne downe <hi>in ſchedula Pipe,</hi> &amp; not already receiued, nor totted vpon the accompt of any Sheriffe; nor granted, nor affigned, nor to be granted, or aſſigned, as aforeſaid, ſhall by this free, gracious, &amp; generall pardon, be tree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; clearely, to all intents and purpoſes, exonerated, pardoned, and diſcharged, &amp; that from henceforth, no further proceſſe ſhal iſſue for levying or collecting the ſame.</p>
            <p>And yet neuertheleſſe, all Eſtreats of ſuch Fines, Iſſues, and Americaments, as be now pardoned by this Act. &amp; which be alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy eſtreated forth of the Court of Exchequer, &amp; bee remaining in the hands of the Sheriffe, Under-ſheriffe, or Bayliffe, for collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſame Fines, Iſſues, &amp; Imerciaments; ſhall vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of the ſame Eſtracts, be orderly charged, and deliuered by Scrowes into the Office of the Pipe, in the Court of Exchequer, as heretofore hath beene accuſtomed; to the intent, that thereupon order may be taken, that his Maieſtie may be truely anſwered, of all ſuch Fines, Iſſues, and Amerciaments, not by this Act par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and which any Sheriffe, Under-ſheriffe, Bayliffe, or other Officer, or Miniſter hath receiued, or ought to anſwere by force or colour, of any ſuch Eſtreat, Proceſſe, or precept, to him, or them made, for the levying thereof: and yet that not withſtanding, all &amp; euery Sheriffe and Sheriffes, and other accomptant, vpon his or
<pb facs="tcp:1260:8"/>their Petition or petitions, to be made, for the allowance of any ſuch Fines, Iſſues, &amp; amerciaments, as by this Act is pardoned, ſhall haue all and euery ſuch his, and their petition allowed, in his and their accompt and accompts, without paying any Fee, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to any Officer, Clerke, or other Miniſter, for the making, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring, or allowing of any ſuch petition or petitions; any vſage or cuſtome to the contrary thereof, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon, all ſuch perſons as bee, and remaine ſtill attainted, or condemned, and not already pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, of, or for any Rebellion, or levying of Marre, or of, or for any conſpiracy of any Rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or levying of Marre, within this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, or in any other the kings Dominions.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted all falſe forging and counterfeiting of any Commiſſion, or Commiſſions, to enquire of any Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Hereditaments. And alſo all falſe forging and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting, of any vntrue Certificate, or returne of any Commiſſion or Commiſſions, obtayned, or gotten forth of any Court or Courts, or by warrant from the Lord Deputie, or other chiefe Gouernour or Gouernours of this Realme; to enquire of any Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or other things whatſoeuer. And all manner falſifying of any particular, or of any Bill or Bills, Fyant or Fyants, ſigned by his Maieſtie, or by his Deputy, or other chiefe Gouernour or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nernours, Commiſſioner or Commiſſioners, in that behalf autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, after the engroſſing thereof, and before the paſſing the ſame vnto the Great Seale.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this pardon, all goods, chattles, debts, actions, and ſuits, already forfeited, or whereof any right, or tittle is accrued, and growne to the kings Maieſtie, by reaſon of any Out lawrie, whereof the kings Maieſtie, by his Higneſſe Letters Pattents, or otherwiſe, hath before the laſt day of this preſent ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Parliament, made any grant, covenant, or promiſe, to any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that it ſhall and may be lawfull, to, and for all and euery Clerke, and other Officers of the kings Courts, to award and make Writs of <hi>Capias ut lagatum,</hi> at the ſuite of the party plaintiffe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch perſons out-lawed, as be pardoned by this Act, to the intent to compell the defendant and defendants, to make anſwere to the plaintiffe or plaintiffs, at whoſe ſuite, he, or they were out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed: And that euery perſon ſo out-lawed, ſhall ſue a Writ of <hi>Scire facias,</hi> againſt the party or partyes, at whoſe ſuite, he, or they were ſo out-lawed before this Pardon, in that behalfe ſhal be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to him, or them that is ſo out-lawed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, and bee it enacted by the authority of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament, That this Act of generall Pardon, ſhall not in any wiſe extend to any perſon out-lawed vpon any Writ of <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ad ſatiſfaciendum,</hi> vntill ſuch times, as the party ſo out-lawed,
<pb facs="tcp:1260:8"/>ſhall latiffie, or otherwiſe agree with the party, at whoſe ſuite the ſame perſon was ſo out-lawed, or condemned.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, and be it enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that neither this Act, nor any thing therin contained, ſhall not extend to pardon or diſcharge any offence committed or done by any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, Captaine, or other perſon whatſoeuer, in the corrupt taking, or hauing of any Money, or other gift or reward, for the changing, releaſing, or diſcharging of any Souldiour, preſt, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſerue his Maieſtie, in defence of the Realme, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted, that this Act, nor any thing therein contayned, ſhall not extend, or be conſtrued, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, or diſcharge any Debt, Accompt, Fine, Amerciament, Arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, or other dutie, for which any Seiſure, or Enſtallment hath beene made, &amp; vpon ſuch Seiſure or Enſtallment, any thing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to his Maieſtie, ſithence the beginning of his Maieſties Raigne; nor to pardon or diſcharge any Recognizance, Obligation or Bond, which is not yet forfeited, or being forfeited, is already giuen, granted, or aſſigned by his Maieſtie, or by his Letters, or Marrant vnder his pridy Signet, directed to be giuen, granted, or aſſigned vnto any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; bee it enacted by the authority aforeſaid: that if any of the grants, made, or directed to be made, as aforeſaid, of any debts, duties, penalties, or ſummes of money, mentioned in the aforeſaid Exceptions, or any of them ſhal be hereafter ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, revoked, or otherwiſe determined, or avoyded. That then, and from thenceforth, the ſaid debts, duties penalties, &amp; ſummes of money, ſhall by this gracious and free Pardon, be pardoned and diſcharged, as if no ſuch clauſe had beene inſerted in any of the ſaid Exceptions.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
